A Guide to the James Rogers McConnell Memorial Collections
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence
  - Letters from James Rogers McConnell to Marcelle Guérin
    - James R. McConnell, Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Jan 9; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [no time to one's self; only seven men ahead of him when he arrived so he started flight training in three days; start by rolling in a Penguin, a machine that won't leave the ground; [Lawrence] Rumsey, an American; awaiting the arrival of [Willis Bradley] Haviland; happy over their time together in Paris]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Jan 13; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [passing through Penguin or rolling classes and will be taking short jumps into the air the following week; [ ] Rumsey's mishap with his machine; going to try to take his brevet on a Bleriot; wants to be breveted so that he will have six days permission in order to see her]
    - James R. McConnell, Ecole Militaire D'Aviation, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Jan 18; 4 p. on 1 l. w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [lieutenant in division smashed a machine; standards have been lowered since his arrival; learn on the most difficult, the Bleriot, and do not get practice on the double command machines; go into the air alone]
    - James R. McConnell, Ecole Militaire D'Aviation, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Jan 24; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [spent first quarter libre in Pau with the crowd; seven wrecks today; should have brevet in sixteen days; going to slow down until he gets the alterrissage better; Russian Ballet wonderful, especially knowing Marcelle was there]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, Centre de Paul, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Jan 28; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [Paul [Rockwell]; start on his voyages in a week; completed stunts required for a civilian brevet; may be breveted in ten days; uniform; wonders how one shoots out of an aeroplane without losing control]
    - James R. McConnell, Monte-de-Marson (Landes), to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916 ante Feb 5] (Box Box 1)
      [lost his way and landed in this place; Landes looks like North Carolina]
    - James R. McConnell, Monte-de-Marson, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Feb 5; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [amusing time with people in this town; hopes of being breveted in two days; Marcelle being exposed to the Zeppelin attacks; promises to see her before going to the front]
    - James R. McConnell, Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916 Feb 7] (Box Box 1)
      [returned via his triangle route; making his altitudes, and then being breveted]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Feb 29; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [numerous orders coming through daily; Americans to be perfectioned at Belleville or on Candrons; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell], [William] Thaw, and others now in Belleville; doing well on the Nieuport; [William] Thaw, [Elliot Christopher] Cowdin, and [Norman] Prince have been put on Nieuports; humorous rantings on being adamant about wanting to be put on the Nieuport; does not have the Belleville school to pass, so will go to Le Bourget and then to the front; supposes there are many wounded at her hospital because of the Verdun attack]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Mar 2; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [no rule on perfectionment makes their training much longer; must be proficient in firing and have target practice every day; will shoot with a mitrailleuse; [Lawrence] Rumsey, the American has disappeared for a week; many Americans have deserted; wants to go to Toul; will have to report to Belleville since the move of the General Reserve; comments on his unseemly conduct on the last day in Paris]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Mar 9; 7 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [slated for the Nieuport; Vidart told him he would pass from the Moran tomorrow; description of his flight and landing; return of [Lawrence] Rumsey, who is in the infantry prison of Pau for fifteen days; [Norman] Prince has pull with the captain; comments on Marcelle's father and mother seeing them together; offers to write her at the Ambulance instead of her home]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Neuilly-sur-Seine, 1916 Mar 17; 4 p. on 1 l. (Box Box 1)
      [on the 23 meter Nieuport for several days and will soon go to the 18 meter; requested to go to Toul through Captain Watt; reminicense about their walk in the Bois; thoughts of going to the Russian front; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell] held up by the American Escadrille; advantage of possessing a lot of machines]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Mar 26; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [Marcelle's ailing ankle; little time left on the Nieuport; hopes to be called to the front but men who left there are tied up at Plaissey-Belleville; Watt leaving for Australian flying corps; Le Bourlis wounded; mishaps of machines falling; description of soldiers passing French officers with the goose step; description of his flight as he started a spiral at 1,000 meters and lost control; [Willis Bradley] Haviland to be breveted in a week]
    - James R. McConnell, [Section Aviaton, Pau] to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Mar 28; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [news of the recovery of Elizabeth "Betty" [Baldwin], first thought dead, who was seriously wounded during a torpedo attack on her ship, and is in the hospital at Winereux in Pas de Calais]
    - James R. McConnell, [Section Aviation, Pau] to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Mar 29; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [relieved that Betty [Baldwin] is expected to recover; describes the terrible accident in which Le Comte, an éléve pilot making an altitude on a Bleriot, was seriously wounded]
    - James R. McConnell, Aviation Militaire, Centre de Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Apr 4; 3 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [discussion of having feelings of depression; marked improvement of Betty [Baldwin]; to be sent to reserve as soon as his perfectionment on the Neiuport is finished; awaiting the return of Lieutenant Chavane before leaving for Plessis-Belleville; thoughts on his accomplishments in aviation school; letter from Mary Lines about Betty Baldwin's condition]
    - James R. McConnell, Division Nieuport, Aviation Militaire, Plessis-Belleville, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Apr 10; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [[Charles Chocteau] Johnson and [Lawrence] Rumsey went to Paris; probably will get on the "Baby" [Nieuport] rightaway because of his hours on the Nieuport; more on his unseemly conduct in Paris; camp in in the war zone; American Escadrille to leave for front this week; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell]; Mary Lines; Betty [Baldwin]; man killed in machine when the gasoline tank exploded]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Apr 20; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [arrived in Luxeuil after traveling to Rosnay, Rheims, and Epernay; news of sixty-two pilots killed; good conditions at camp; escadrille has beautiful equipment and over seventy men but only ten pilots; high regard given to pilots]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Apr 26; with APCS, 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [encloses postcard of Luxeuil; mentions [Norman] Prince, [William] Thaw, and [Elliot Christopher] Cowdin; "Baby" Nieuports have not arrived; Norman Prince smashed the 18 meter Nieuport before leaving for Paris; first pracatice with a mitrailleuse; description of tour from Belfort into Alsace to look over landing places; German dropped three bombs and there were no machines to use to bring him down]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 May 6; 3 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [thermal baths running short; [Elliot Christopher] Cowdin decorated with the Médaille Militaire; attendance of funerals; [Elliot Christopher] Cowdin and [Norman] Prince going to Paris; arrival of five "Baby" Nieuports but not those for [Victor] Chapman, [Elliot Christopher] Cowdin, [Norman] Prince, and himself; first trial run by Kiffin [Yates Rockwell]; description of the beautiful "Rosa" who serves beer in a café; [William] Thaw; Betty [Baldwin] improved remarkably; Walter Lovell wants to get into aviation]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] May 11 (Box Box 1)
      [new machine running beautifully; awaiting arrival of his machine gun; "Rosa"]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 May 13; 8 p. on 2 p., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [machine climbs well and mitrailleuse is ready; [Victor] Chapman and himself were the Luxeuil guard; description of any early morning "sortie en escadrille" in his "Baby" Nieuport as well as the surrounding view of the sky and ground; [Kiffin Yates] Rockwell, [Victor] Chapman, and [William] Thaw being shot at by German planes; Army moving picture outfit to take them for the French propaganda in America and they have staged a big show in connection with the bombardment machines; recovery of Betty Baldwin]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 May 19; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [orders to go to Verdun; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell] downed a German aviator that was firing at them; [William] Thaw had a fight the day before]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] May 28; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [leaving for Bar le Duc; [William] Thaw brought down a Fokker and was wounded in the arm; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell] was wounded in the face; [Norman] Prince and [Bert] Hall broke their machines to splinters; going to pass by Toul so as to fly over the Bois le Prêtre where there should be some Germans since the Toul avion de chasse outfit is at Verdun; "scheme of dropping a bomb with compliments of Betty Baldwin"; to regulate his mitrailleuse]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 May 30; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [addresses her concern for him; plans to go to Toul; Lt. DeLaage [de Meux] flew down from Bar le Duc; inquires of moving pictures about the unit; relates that "Mac" is printed on the side of his machine; [William] Thaw]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Jun 4; 4 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [description of first combat; encountered fourteen German airplanes; five of which mounted to the attack; Germans dropped a great number of bombs, killing fifty people and wounding four times that; Germans used explosive bullets; old ambulance section picked up the wounded; [Walter] Lovell leaving to join the aviation corps; relates his own encounter with a German plane and losing his direction and subsequent crash landing at a French aviation center in St. Dizier; news of Betty [Baldwin]]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Luxeuil, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Jun 13; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [relates looking for a German sighted over Vaux, describes view of Verdun through the clouds; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell]; [Walter] Lovell; Paul [Rockwell]; Betty [Baldwin]'s recovery]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916 Jun 18]; 3 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [William] Thaw; describes the ordeal of [Victor] Chapman as he attacked a German plane over the lines and was surrounded by four others; [Horace Clyde] Balsley and [Elliot Christopher] Cowdin at first missing following a fight but then returned; [Norman] Prince reeturned; describes an accident killing two men in a Brequet; [Walter] Lovell]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Jun 23; 4 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [Victor Chapman killed in a fight over the German lines against superior numbers; praises Chapman; [William] Thaw; Paul [Rockwell]; news that [Horace Clyde] Balsley is dying then news that he is better; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell]]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Jun 27; 4 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [Kiffin [Yates Rockwell] received the Croix de Guerre and the Medaille]; [Charles Chocteau] Johnson, [Horace Clyde] Balsley, and himself passed sergeant]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, to Marcelle Guérin, Haute Savoie, 1916 Jul 12; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [describes their flying maneuvers; saw black plane with white crosses of the famous Captain [ ] Balke; Kiffin [Yates Rockwell], [Bert] Hall, and "Billy" [William Thaw ?] were decorated; Betty Baldwin]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N.124], to Marcelle Guérin, Haute Savoie, 1916 Jul 16; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [romantic letter]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N.124], to Marcelle Guérin, Haute Savoie, 1916 Jul 25; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [ [Bert] Hall brought down a German in their lines; Lieutenant [Chaput?] was wounded; Nungesser with them; [Walter] Lovell is now at Buc training; news of the Legion going into the battle of Somme 3,000 strong and coming out 800, with several Americans being killed or wounded]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Haute Savoie, 1916 Aug 5; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [asked for permission for the 15th to go to Paris; only four machines running in the escadrille; inquires of a Polly Root who is acting as secretary of the French Wounded Emergency Relief Fund]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Aug 25; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [leaving for a two-week stay at hospital for a recurrence of rheumatism; mentions seeing Gustave Bauer]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Aug 27; APCS (Box Box 1)
      [mentions treatment in the hospital]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124 [hospital], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Aug 31; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [received books; describes two arrangments at the hospital mentioning a portable barracks with a straw mattress and bad conditions and the infirmary with an orderly in attendance; eclopé horses there]
    - James R. McConnell, [hospital], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Sep 3; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [to attend the concert where he will hear the Rumanian national anthem and Faust; escadrille is leaving Bar le Duc; read Train 8.47 [
      Le Train de 8 H. 47; La Vie de Caserne
      by Georges Courteline]; comments on her "young girl's illusion about romance"; mentions Yvonne]
    - James R. McConnell, Hôpital Mixte, Vitry le François, Marne, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Sep 7; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [comments on
      Fragments from France
      [by Bruce Bairnsfather]; mentions his back injury and conditions at the hospital]
    - James R. McConnell, Hôpital Mixte, Vitry le François, Marne, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Sep 12; 3 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [news of the big offensive; 2,000 motor lorries passed through]
    - James R. McConnell, Hôpital Mixte, Vitry le François, Marne, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Sep 17; 4 p. on 1 l. w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [mentions his back condition; mentions Yvonne having vacation]
    - James R. McConnell, Pneumatique, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916 Sep 29]; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (electrostatic copy) (Box Box 1)
      [Paul [Rockwell] despondent over death of his brother Kiffin [Yates Rockwell] while attacking a German at an altitude of 3,500 meters; describes the attack and aftermath during which Rockwell was killed]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916 Oct 8]; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [trouble with his back; news of [Paul] Pavelka and [Norman] Prince]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Nov 16; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [trouble with stiff back, making it difficult to fly; extremely cold, fierce weather; Germans come over nearly every night as it is a big aviation center; mentions bombing of a hangar which burnt up eight machines and caused injuries]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Nov 26; 1 p. (Box Box 1)
      [plans to act as witness for Paul [Rockwell]'s wedding]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Dec 7; 2 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [comments on Paul [Rockwell]'s wedding and seeing her there; moving to a point on the line nearer to Paris; mentions [Paul] Pavelka, Hé:lène Dé Bouchet, and Betty Baldwin]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Dec 14; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [order from a general that a few machines must be over the lines despite the weather; describes the flight of [Gervais Raoul Victor] Lufbery and [Paul] Pavelka this day; [Ronald Wood] Hoskier joined the escadrille; inquires of [Lawrence] Rumsey]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916] Dec 15; 2 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [problems with flying in bad weather; moving to a new post]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1916 Dec 26; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [thanks for the cigarette case; received 200 Dimitrinos and a cigarette case for a table from Paul [Rockwell]; flight in the rain; [Paul] Pavelka sick and smashed up on landing; [Gervais Raoul Victor] Lufbery laid up with rheumatism in his back; witty description of "salvation army" formed by Lufbery and 'Skipper']
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1917 Jan 2]; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [news of Howard's death; arrival of "Bill" [William Thaw] and [Charles Chocteau] Johnson; [Dudley Lawrence] Hill and Paul [Ayres Rockwell] left for the United States; escadrille has rotten reputation in Paris for drinking; comments on the cigarette case; mentions "Whiskey" [the lion cub mascot of the squadron]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1917 Jan 7; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [[William] Thaw and [Charles Chocteau] Johnson returned from the United States; first flying day in a long time with ten strong; description of flight activity between escadrille and Germans; postponed leaved so [Gervais Raoul Victor] Lufbery could take his]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1917 Feb 10; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [orders not to cross the lines; he and Lieutenant de Laage [de Meux] have volunteered to go "'sausage' chasing"; Biglow here now, playing the piano; had wonderful time in Paris with her; [Paul] Pavelka; Fred Prince going to Paris]
    - James R. McConnell, H. O. E. 7/1, Ambulance 6/10, S. P. 200, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1917 Feb 14; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [in hospital "with the itch"; description of hospital and patients]
    - James R. McConnell, Escadrille N. 124, Ho E. 7/1 Amb. 6/10, S. P. 200, to Marcelle Guérin, [1917] Feb 20; 4 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [meeting men of difference races in the world; mentions Captain [Bert ?] Hall, Hélène, "Bill" [William Thaw], and "Whiskey"]
    - James R. McConnell, Hô E. 7/1, Section Z, S. P. 200, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1917 Feb 26; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [charming description of days mimicking spring; includes excerpt from a letter of Betty Baldwin of a glowing description of Marcelle]
    - James R. McConnell, [Escadrille N. 124], to Marcelle Guérin, Nice, 1917 Mar 16; 4 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [comments on his article in the
      English World's Work
      and the
      American W. M.
      season for flying now open with new assignments such as observation work too far in the lines for the slow machines; he [Walter] Lovell, Willis [Haviland], and others went 35 kilometers inside to do reconnaissance; Germans are preparing to withdraw all along this front and retire to the Hidenburg line, thereby evacuating a fifth of the ground they hold in France; description of the evacuation; Navarre back on the front and at their field]
  - Letters from James Rogers McConnell to Paul Ayres Rockwell
    - James R. McConnell, Paris, to Paul A. Rockwell, Neuilly-sur-Seine, 1915 Apr 21; APCS (Box Box 2)
      [trip from Nancy to their post has been postponed until morning]
    - James R. McConnell, Nancy, to Paul A. Rockwell, Neuilly-sur-Seine, [1915 Apr 21]; APCS (written in French) (Box Box 2)
      [Nancy is beautiful]
    - James R. McConnell, Mirecourt Vosges, to Paul A. Rockwell, Neuilly-sur- Seine, [1915 Apr 22]; APCS (Box Box 2)
      [going to Pont-à-Mousson tomorrow; in between two German salients]
    - James R. McConnell, Pont-à-Mousson, to Paul A. Rockwell, Neuilly-sur- Seine, [1915] Apr 23; APCS (Box Box 2)
      [Germans attacked, killing two children and a woman and destroying several places]
    - James R. McConnell, Mirecourt Vosges, to Paul A. Rockwell, Neuilly-sur- Seine, Sunday [1915 Apr 25]; APCS (Box Box 2)
      [passed through the most wonderful country; made 230 kilos through patchwork lands of soldier's graves and houses wrecked by the Germans]
    - James R. McConnell, Paris, to Paul A. Rockwell, Paris, 1915 Apr 26; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 2)
      [base near the trenches; damage at the station caused by German obus; advance post under a good deal of fire; living quarters comfortable; description of an American engineer named Decker; large fight expected soon]
    - James R. McConnell, Neuilly-sur-Seine, to Paul A. Rockwell, Paris, 1915 Apr 27; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 2)
      [uncensored letter: description of an attack on the base; French detrained trainloads of troops at the base in preparation for an attack in the Bois-le-Prêtre at Pont-à-Mousson; description of ambulance trip with Willis [Haviland], writing of the wounded and the damage caused by shelling; expecting worse when they have big fight at Pont-à-Mousson; annoyed with military stuff, such as saluting all day and answering foolish questions for drunken soldiers]
    - James R. McConnell to Paul A. Rockwell, Paris, [1915] May 3; 12 p. on 3 l., w/env. (Box Box 2)
      [fight resulted in four trenches being taken and a hundred and fifty Germans; ambulances work between the artillery and the trenches; description of the shelling and its damage; description of beautiful scenery of 'La Belle France' on the way to their evacuation cases; terrible injuries caused by the crapouillots tossed into the trenches; kodaks taken from them so no pictures; advice for Paul's upcoming marriage; met a "village belle" who has promised him he may call on her at night]
    - James R. McConnell, Pont-à-Mousson, to Paul A. Rockwell, 1915 May 8; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 2)
      [another heavy bombardment yesterday; describes conditions under which they work at night; discusses village life, with stores and factories running and cafes crowded; sleeping quarters at base and advance point comfortable; received letters from Marcelle Guérin and Elizabeth "Betty" Baldwin; one hundred and fifty Germans working at the base as a "White Wings" gang]
    - James R. McConnell to Paul A. Rockwell, Paris, 1915 May 14; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 2)